<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Howto on Michał Kowol</title>
    <link>https://michalkowol.github.io/tags/howto/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Howto on Michał Kowol</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 21 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://michalkowol.github.io/tags/howto/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>How to configure LB-LINK</title>
      <link>https://michalkowol.github.io/posts/2017-01-21-lb-link/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://michalkowol.github.io/posts/2017-01-21-lb-link/</guid>
      <description>Overview Do you want to change WiFi to regular cable connection. Or you need cheap WiFI amplifier? This post is for you!
You can by LB-LINK BL-MP01 for only 13$ (52 PLN). It is really cheap and it does it work.
Repeater (client mode)  If you want to change WiFi to regular cable connection you need to switch device to Repeater mode.  Connect power and Ethernet cable. Make sure power mode is on.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>/boot 100% and can&#39;t purge</title>
      <link>https://michalkowol.github.io/posts/2016-11-07-linux-headers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://michalkowol.github.io/posts/2016-11-07-linux-headers/</guid>
      <description>Overview Sometimes, during updating your ubuntu, you get a problem with full /boot directory. The sandard ways to clear that directories fail and you need to find better solution to this problem.
Solution  sudo apt-get install - fix-broken should fail but list unused packets free them one by one using sudo dpkg --purge .... If a packet refuse to uninstall due to dependencies, just advance to the next one.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to server cifi shared folder using nginx.</title>
      <link>https://michalkowol.github.io/posts/2016-11-07-nginx-cifs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://michalkowol.github.io/posts/2016-11-07-nginx-cifs/</guid>
      <description>Setup Create folder /media/storage/dir/
mkdir -p /media/storage/dir/  Next, mount shared directory. uid and gid are very important because without this you will get 403 Forbidden.
sudo mount -t cifs -o uid=www-data,gid=www-data,ro,username=username,password=password //10.0.0.2/shared/ /media/storage/dir/   -t cifs - type of fs (cifs - Common Internet File System, also known as smb) uid - specific user gid - specific groutp ro - read-only rw - read-write username - shared directory username password - shared directory password  Modify nginx config (/etc/nginx/sites-available/somefile)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Set locale on your linux</title>
      <link>https://michalkowol.github.io/posts/2016-11-07-locale/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://michalkowol.github.io/posts/2016-11-07-locale/</guid>
      <description>Overview If you installed new, server ubuntu distribiution, you could have problem with localces on your computer.
Locale check which locales are supported:
locale -a  and install
apt-get install language-pack-XX  where XX is language code - in example language-pack-pl or language-pack-ru
Alternative You can generate locale using locale-gen
sudo locale-gen pl_PL sudo locale-gen pl_PL.UTF-8  then, run this update comand
sudo update-locale  References How do I add locale to ubuntu server?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Samba (smb)</title>
      <link>https://michalkowol.github.io/posts/2016-11-04-smb-howto/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://michalkowol.github.io/posts/2016-11-04-smb-howto/</guid>
      <description>Overview Samba is a free software re-implementation of the SMB/CIFS networking protocol. Samba provides file and print services for various Microsoft Windows clients and can integrate with a Microsoft Windows Server domain, either as a Domain Controller (DC) or as a domain member. As of version 4, it supports Active Directory and Microsoft Windows NT domains.
Configuration On Ubuntu configuration file is located in /etc/samba/smb.conf. You need root privileges to edit it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Backups with rsnapshot</title>
      <link>https://michalkowol.github.io/posts/2016-11-03-backup-with-rsnapshot/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://michalkowol.github.io/posts/2016-11-03-backup-with-rsnapshot/</guid>
      <description>Docker test enviroment Dockerfile:
FROM ubuntu:17.10 RUN apt-get update &amp;amp;&amp;amp; apt-get install -y rsnapshot ENTRYPOINT [&amp;quot;/bin/bash&amp;quot;]  and run it with
docker build -t ubuntu-rsnapshot . docker run --name ubuntu-rsnapshot-bash -it ubuntu-rsnapshot  to attach another terminal you can use
docker exec -it ubuntu-rsnapshot-bash /bin/bash  Rsnapshot configuration You can find configuration in /etc/rsnapshot.conf
The most interesing parts of config:
config_version 1.2 cmd_cp	/bin/cp cmd_rm	/bin/rm cmd_rsync	/usr/bin/rsync cmd_ssh	/usr/bin/ssh cmd_logger	/usr/bin/logger verbose	2 loglevel	3 logfile	/var/log/rsnapshot.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Midnight Commander</title>
      <link>https://michalkowol.github.io/posts/2016-11-03-midnight-commander/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://michalkowol.github.io/posts/2016-11-03-midnight-commander/</guid>
      <description>Overview Midnight Commander is based on versatile text interfaces, such as Ncurses or S-Lang, which allows it to work on a regular console, inside an X Window terminal, over SSH connections and all kinds of remote shells.
Shorcuts  Ctrl + x, q quick preview (x = comman, q = quick view) Shift + F6 rename file Ctrl + o open/close terminal Ctrl + s cd in active panel Esc + c quick cd Esc + i open same directory in another panel Ctrl + r refresh  Configure open as View/Open Menu: Command &amp;gt; Edit extension file</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>nmap</title>
      <link>https://michalkowol.github.io/posts/2016-11-03-nmap/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://michalkowol.github.io/posts/2016-11-03-nmap/</guid>
      <description>Overview Nmap (&amp;ldquo;Network Mapper&amp;rdquo;) is a free and open source utility for network discovery and security auditing. Many systems and network administrators also find it useful for tasks such as network inventory, managing service upgrade schedules, and monitoring host or service uptime. Nmap uses raw IP packets in novel ways to determine what hosts are available on the network, what services (application name and version) those hosts are offering, what operating systems (and OS versions) they are running, what type of packet filters/firewalls are in use, and dozens of other characteristics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to: rsync</title>
      <link>https://michalkowol.github.io/posts/2016-10-30-rsync-how-to/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://michalkowol.github.io/posts/2016-10-30-rsync-how-to/</guid>
      <description>Documentation rsync selected options
-a, --archive It is more commonly used than -r (recursive) and is usually what you want to use. -z, --compress With this option, rsync compresses the file data as it is sent to the destination machine -v, --verbose This option increases the amount of information the daemon logs during its startup phase. -x, --one-file-system This tells rsync to avoid crossing a filesystem boundary when recursing. -A, --acls Preserve ACLs (implies -p).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Synology ssh with public key</title>
      <link>https://michalkowol.github.io/posts/2016-10-29-synology/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://michalkowol.github.io/posts/2016-10-29-synology/</guid>
      <description>Generating SSH keys First of all generate SSH private and public keys on your local machine.
local&amp;gt; ssh-keygen -t rsa -b 4096 -C &amp;quot;yourmail@example.com&amp;quot;  New user It is good idea to create dedicated user for rsync.
synology&amp;gt; adduser rsync  SSH with public key on Synology Directories By default Synology sets home directory rights to 777. sshd is very picky and its needs different home directory rights.
synology&amp;gt; chmod 755 /var/services/homes/rsync  Then you need to create the authorized_keys file on Synlogy.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>